Guide to the Pamela Sporn Papers TAM.708
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Pamela Sporn Papers
1990-2015
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Sporn, Pam
TAM.708
0.5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box
832 Gigabytes in 584 computer files
2 DVCAM
29 MiniDV
Pamela Sporn is a documentary filmmaker whose films combine personal narratives and archival materials to tell stories about working-class life. The Pamela Sporn papers contain videos and research materials related to Sporn's documentaries. The bulk of the collection and consists of approximately 400 digital video files as well as research files created by Sporn for her film A Humble Giant: 70 Years Defending Immigrants and Radicals, about immigration lawyer Ira Gollobin. It also includes DVDs of Sporn's documentaries With a Stroke of the Chevata and Disobeying Orders: GI Resistance to the Vietnam War, and analog video footage of interviews from With a Stroke of the Chevata and A Humble Giant.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Pamela Sporn in April 2017. The accession number associated with this gift is 2017.023.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into three series: Series I. A Humble Giant media; Series II. A Humble Giant research and production files; Series III: Other projects. Files within each series are arranged alphabetically.
Biographical Note
Pamela Sporn is a documentary filmmaker whose films combine personal narratives and archival materials to tell stories about working-class life. Sporn was the daughter of labor activists, leftist scholars, and American Communists. In 1964 her father Paul Sporn gained national attention after he was subpoenaed by the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC), and was represented by Ira Gollobin who later inspired Pamela Sporn's work as a documentarian. Sporn's documentaries generally focus on political resistance and the working class. She has produced several documentaries through her production company Grito Productions, including Disobeying Orders: G. I. Resistance to The Vietnam War (1990); Remembering the Mamoncillo (2007), about Afro-Cuban culture in New York City; With a Stroke of the Chaveta (2007), about Cuban cigar factory workers; Detroit 48202: Conversations Along a Postal Route (2017); and A Humble Giant: Seventy Years Defending Immigrants and Radicals (still in production at the time of donation), about immigration lawyer and activist Ira Gollobin.
Scope and Contents
The Pamela Sporn Papers consist of videos and research materials used by Pamela Sporn in her documentary films. The bulk of the collection consists of approximately 400 digital video files created by Sporn for her film A Humble Giant: 70 Years Defending Immigrants and Radicals, about immigration lawyer Ira Gollobin. These files include interviews and background footage from the documentary, which have been arranged by Sporn by individual and topic. There is also video footage from Ira Gollobin's 2008 memorial service and a 2005 National Lawyers Guild dinner. The collection also includes research files, budgets, fundraising, and promotional materials related to the production of the documentary. In addition to the digital video files, there are DVCAM and MiniDV cassettes that contain additional interviews.
The collection also includes MiniDV video cassettes of interviews Sporn conducted while producing Con el toque de la chaveta, which documents the experiences of workers in Cuban cigar factories.
Other materials included in this collection consist of photocopies related to the website Unfriendly Witness: Standing Up to HUAC, which Sporn created to document her family's experience with the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC).
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
An access terminal for born-digital materials in the collection is available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Researchers may view an item's original container and/or carrier, but the physical carriers themselves are not available for use because of preservation concerns.
Related Materials
For more information about Ira Gollobin please see the Ira Gollobin Papers (TAM 278) and the Records of the American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born (TAM 086), both held by New York University Special Collections. There is also a collection of Ira Gollobin's papers at the New York Public Library Archives and Manuscripts (MssCol 6133).
Appraisal
In October 2025, commercial DVDs of Disobeying Orders: GI Resistance to the Vietnam War and Con el toque de la chaveta were removed from Series III. These films are available through the Avery Fisher Center for Music and Media.
Documentary films -- United States.; Emigration and immigration law -- United States.; Foreign workers -- United States; Lawyers -- Political activity -- United States.; Cigar industry -- Employees.; Working class -- History -- 20th century; Gollobin, Ira, 1911-; Grito Productions
- Series I: A Humble Giant media, 2004-2011; 2 DVCAM; 23 MiniDV; 831 Gigabytes in 415 computer files
  Arrangement
  Files are arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains video footage of interviews and events Pamela Sporn filmed for the documentary A Humble Giant about immigration attorney Ira Gollobin. Sporn interviewed Gollobin, his wife Ruth Gollobin, and some of his former clients and affiliates including Henry Foner, Bertell Ollman, Albert Socolov, and Sporn's father Paul Sporn. Topics covered include Gollobin's work with people who were targeted by the House Un-American Activities Committee (HUAC), immigrant rights activism, the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and the Spanish Civil War, and issues regarding the Labor movement and Leftist politics. Sporn also filmed much of Gollobin's memorial service which followed his death in 2008.
  The video in this series was filmed digitally. In addition to video files that were stored on a hard drive there are also DVCAM and MiniDV cassettes.
  - Albert Socolov on Ira Gollobin and the National Lawyers Guild, November 2010-May 2011; cuid36873
  - Bertell Ollman, July 14, 2007; cuid36874
  - Bishop Guy Sansaricq, November 2010; cuid36875
  - Claire Hirsch, March 14, 2009; cuid36872
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, cuid44006 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0020)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      Duration: 42 min
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, cuid44007 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0021)
      Duration: 44 min
  - Eddie Lemansky, October-November 2010; cuid36876
  - Fran Goldin on Ira Gollobin, March 7, 2009; April 24, 2011; cuid44010
    - Electronic Records, March 7, 2009; April 24, 2011; cuid36877
    - Video recording, March 7, 2009; cuid44011 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0017)
      Duration: 43 min
  - Henry Foner on Ira Gollobin, April 15, 2009; September 26, 2009; cuid44012
    - Electronic Records, April 15, 2009; September 26, 2009; cuid36878
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, April 15, 2009; cuid44013 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0013)
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, April 15, 2009; cuid44014 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0014)
      Duration: 21 min
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, September 26, 2009; cuid44015 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0015)
      Duration: 65 min
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, September 26, 2009; cuid44016 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0016)
      Duration: 53 min
  - Ira Gollobin interviews, July 23, 2007; April 19, 2011; cuid44017
    - Electronic Records, July 23, 2007; April 19, 2011; cuid36879
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, July 23, 2007; cuid44018 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0003)
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, July 23, 2007; cuid44019 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0004)
      Duration: 17 min
  - Ira Gollobin Interview: Case of Paul Sporn-HUAC Hearing 1964, May 27, 2004; cuid36868
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, cuid44008 (Box 1, Dvcam 708.0001)
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, cuid44009 (Box 1, Dvcam 708.0002)
  - Ira Gollobin: American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born, September 8, 2007; cuid36870 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0006)
  - Ira Gollobin memorial service, July 19, 2008; cuid44020
    - Electronic Records, cuid36880
    - Video recording -- Camera 1, cuid44021 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0009)
      Duration: 47 min
    - Video recording -- Camera 2, Tape 1, cuid44022 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0010)
      Duration: 57 min
    - Video recording -- Camera 2, Tape 2, cuid44023 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0011)
    - Video recording -- Reception, cuid44024 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0012)
      Duration: 38 min
  - Ira Kurzban, April 19, 2011; cuid36881
  - Jocelyn McCalla, October 2010-April 2011; cuid36882
  - Levi Laub, July 15, 2011; cuid36883
  - Matti Mattson on Ira Gollobin and the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, April 25, 2009; April 24, 2011; cuid44025
    - Electronic Records, April 25, 2009; April 24, 2011; cuid36884
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, April 25, 2009; cuid44026 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0018)
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, April 25, 2009; cuid44027 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0019)
  - May Day, 2011; cuid36885
  - National Lawyers Guild Dinner, 2005; cuid44028
    - Electronic Records, cuid36886
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, cuid44029 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0025)
      Duration: 59 min
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, cuid44030 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0026)
      Duration: 14 min
  - Paul Sporn, April 24, 2011; cuid36887
  - Ralph Shapiro, December 11, 2009; cuid36871
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, cuid44031 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0007)
      Duration: 63 min
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, cuid44032 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0008)
      Duration: 6 min
  - Rulx Jean-Bart, April 19, 2011; cuid36888
  - Ruth Gollobin, September 7, 2008 - April 20, 2011; cuid44033
    - Electronic Records, September 7, 2008 - April 20, 2011; cuid36889 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0022-708.0024)
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, September 7, 2008; cuid44034 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0022)
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, September 8, 2008; cuid44035 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0023)
      Duration: 41 min
    - Video recording -- Tape 3, September 8, 2008; cuid44036 (Box 1, Hdv 708.0024)
      Duration: 35 min
- Series II: A Humble Giant research and production files, 2007-2015; 431.5 Megabytes in 169 computer files.
  This series includes documents created in the process of planning the production of A Humble Giant and documents Sporn gathered while doing background research about Ira Gollobin. Planning documents include budgets, project descriptions, fundraising materials, production stills, and interview questions. Research files include both materials related directly to Ira Gollobin and materials related to his interests and areas of expertise such as immigration law, the House Un-American Activities Committee, Haiti, and the Spanish Civil War.
  - 1963 Student trip to Cuba, May 17, 2011; cuid36890
  - A Humble Giant Wordpress site, 2010-2011; cuid36891
  - American Committee for the Protection of Foreign Born, 2009-2011; cuid36892
  - Archival footage, January 30, 2011; cuid36893
  - Articles about Ira Gollobin, 2008-2015; cuid36894
  - Broken Justice Report on Immigration Detainees, June 30, 2009; cuid36895
  - Budgets, 2009-2012; cuid36896
  - Ellis Island, 2010-2011; cuid36897
  - Fundraising, 2009-2011; cuid36898
  - Gollobin Memorial remarks, July 6, 2008; cuid36899
  - Haiti, February 7, 2011; cuid36900
  - House Un-American Activities Committee, 2004-2011; cuid36901
  - Images, 2009-2012; cuid36902
  - Immigration articles, 2009-2011; cuid36903
  - Interviews, 2008-2011; cuid36904
  - Ira Gollobin Papers finding aid, July 7, 2008; cuid36905
  - Lincoln articles, 2009; cuid36906
  - Notes on resources in the Tamiment Library, July 31, 2009; cuid36907
  - Production planning, 2009; cuid36908
  - Production stills, 2010; cuid36909
  - Spanish Civil War, 2007-2010; cuid36910
  - Synopses, 2008-2009; cuid36911
- Series III: Other projects, 1990-2007; 6 MiniDV
  This series contains footage from Pamela Sporn's film Con el toque de la chaveta. There is also a printed copy of Sporn's website titled "Unfriendly Witness: Standing Up to HUAC" which documented her family's experience with the House Un-American Activities Committee.
  - Con el toque de la chaveta footage, undated; cuid36869
    - Video recording -- Tape 1, cuid44037 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0027)
      Duration: 32 min
    - Video recording -- Tape 2, cuid44038 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0028)
    - Video recording -- Tape 3, cuid44039 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0029)
    - Video recording -- Tape 4, cuid44040 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0030)
    - Video recording -- Tape 5, cuid44041 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0031)
      Duration: 29 min
    - Video recording -- Tape 6, cuid44042 (Box 1, Minidv 708.0032)
      Duration: 34 min
  - Unfriendly Witness: Standing Up to HUAC, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 157, Folder 18)